Guide to the Remsen and Schenk family papers 1985.017
Brooklyn Historical Society
Remsen and Schenk family papers
1698-1837
Brooklyn Historical Society
Dickerson, Barbara
Remsen family
Schenk family
1985.017
2.1 Linear Feet in one flat box.
The Remsen and Schenk family papers are comprised of various land and legal documents, including deeds, mortgages, wills, and conveyances to land primarily in Brooklyn. Most documents concern property owned by the Remsen and Schenk families.
Box 1
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Barbara Dickerson, 1982.
Arrangement
Upon reporocessing in 2024, the original 1985 arrangement was retained. The collection is arranged into four series. Series 1 consists of documents relating to the Remsen family. Series 2 consists of documents relating to the Schenk family. Series 3 consists of other Brooklyn land documents. The items are housed together by series except for oversize items, which are together in their own folder.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Historical Society Genealogical vertical files (ARC.313), Folder: Remsen
Garrit S.K. Remsen bankbook (1973.175)
Garrit S.K. Remsen accounts and collection records for Flatlands School District No.2 (1977.493)
Willets and Remsen lease (1977.627)
Teunis G. Bergen and Bergen family collection (ARC.006)
March, Middagh, and Sands families property records (1974.038)
Lefferts family papers (ARC.145)
Francis Skillman papers (ARC.280)
Newtown, Queens County deeds (1977.514)
Scope and Contents
The Remsen and Schenk family papers are comprised of various land and legal documents, including deeds, mortgages, wills, and conveyances to land primarily in Brooklyn. Most documents concern property owned by the Remsen and Schenk families. The collection relates to the following farmers: Jacob Remsen (1719-1794), Joris Remsen (1721-1794) Martin Schenk (1796-1823) and Lambert Schenk (1796-1815).
Real property -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Farms -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Mortgages; Conveyances; Deeds; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Wills; Newtown (Queens County, N.Y.); Deeds -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Executors and administrators -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Families -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Farmers -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Farms -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Land titles -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Landowners -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Queens County (N.Y.); Queens County (N.Y.) -- History; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Real property -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Real property -- Ownership -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Roads -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); New Lots (New York, N.Y.); Wallabout (New York, N.Y.); Acquisition of property -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Agriculture -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Agriculture -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Agriculture -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Bonds -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Decedents' estates -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Deeds -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Deeds -- New York (State) -- New York; Executors and administrators -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Families -- New York (State); Families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Families -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Families -- New York (State) -- New York; Farmers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Farmers -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Farms -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Genealogy -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Land grants -- New York (State); Land grants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Land grants -- New York (State) -- New York; Land titles -- New York (State); Land titles -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Land titles -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Land titles -- New York (State) -- New York; Landowners -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Landowners -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Legal documents -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Mortgages -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Property -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Real property -- New York (State); Real property -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Real property -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Real property -- New York (State) -- New York; Real property -- Ownership -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Real property -- Ownership -- New York (State) -- New York; Dickerson, Barbara; Remsen family; Schenk family; Skillman family; Suydam family; Nostrand family; Duryea family; Lefferts family; Lott family; Vandervoort, Peter; Debevoise family; Conselyea family; Hegeman family; Ditmars family; Pettit family; Sands, Joshua
- Series 1: Remsen family
  - Declaration, 1760 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Announcement of Jacob and Joris Remsen that they are claiming the land left to them by their father upon his death. The land is three small parcels on the south side of the road to the ferry, adjoining the property of John Nostrand and Cornelius Duryea in the Town of "Bruckland" near "Flatbush Meadows." The family homestead was apparently named "Crupelbush." This copy was signed by Jacob.
  - Declaration, 1760 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Same as above, except signed by Joris Remsen.
  - Will, 1764 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Rem Remson's will, bequeathing his estate to his brothers Isaac, John, Jacob and Joris, as well as his sisters.
  - Will, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Jacob Remsen's will, bequeathing his estate to his son Isaac and sons-in-law Johannes Debevoise and Samuel Harris.
  - Will, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Joris Remsen's will.
  - Probated will, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    A document signed by Jacobus Lefferts, surrogate of Kings County, declaring Jacob Remsen's will authentic. It lists executors as Isaac Remsen, Johannes Debevoise, and Samuel Harris. Included is a copy of the 1785 will.
  - Probated will, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    A document signed by Jacobus Lefferts, surrogate of Kings County, declaring Joris Remsen's will authentic. It names John Ditmars and Samuel Harris as executors.
  - Deed, 1704 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Jeremiah Remsen to Isaac Remsen for land south of Flatbush.
  - Deed, 1704 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Isaac Remsen purchased 66 acres from Jacob Buys.
  - Deed, 1709 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Isaak [Isaac] Remsen purchased land from Matthys Corvoliuys [?], known as "Cripplebush" in the area known as "Brookland."
  - Deed, 1712 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Isaac Remsen of "Crupplebush" bought 4 acres of land from Cornelius, Johannes, and David van Cats of Bushwyck.
  - Deed, 1714 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Isaac Remsen obtained an "upland swamp" near "Criepelbos" from the Town of Brooklyn. It was bounded on the north by Jeremiah Remsen's land.
  - Deed, 1724 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Isaac Remsen and Jacques Durje [Duryea?] bought 96 acres of land from Joseph Hegeman Tun and Arianje his wife, bound on the northwest by the highway leading from Bushwick to the ferry.
  - Deed, 1730 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Isaak Remse" purchased 6 acres of land in "Bruckland…a-long the road that leadeth to the ferry of New York" from Johannes Cushow.
  - Deed, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Joris Remsen paid Rem Remsen for land in "Crupelbos," Brooklyn.
  - Estate sale notice, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    George Remsen's farm and property in Brooklyn Woods, New Lots, and Bushwick were put up for sale. Johannes Ditmars and Samuel Harris were executors.
  - Document, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    List of heirs of Joris Remsen's estate. Includes dozens of signatures.
- Series 2: Schenk family
  - Will, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Apparently a draft of a will by Martin Schenk [Sr.?] dividing his estate into three parts, to be given to his sons Martin and Lambert and his daughter Anne Schenk Skillman.
  - Bond, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    John Grennelle of Dutchess County and William Nicholl of Islip, Long Island were bound to Martin Schenk [Sr.?] for 400 pounds.
  - Survey, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Survey for Martin and Lambert Schenk of their farms in Brooklyn by Peter Vandervoort.
  - Conveyance, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Road access to Lambert Schenk from Martin and Sarah Schenk. Lambert's copy.
  - Conveyance, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Same as above, except it is Martin and Sarah's copy.
  - Bond, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Martin Schenk bonded to Mercy Conselyea of Bushwick for $400. The bond was paid off in 1811.
  - Bond, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Martin Schenk borrowed $4,125 from Jacobus Suydam of Newtown, Queens County.
  - Mortgage, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Lambert Schenk bought land and a house from Jacobus Suydam of Newtown, Queens County. The property was situated on the road from Newtown to Brooklyn through the "Wallabought" [Wallabout Bay]. It bordered the land of Martin Schenk. The signature is missing from this document.
  - Mortgage, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Martin Schenk purchased land bordering the highway from Bedford to New Lots from James Suydam of Newtown, Queens County.
  - Mortgage, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Martin and Sarah Schenk probably cosigned this mortgage from James Suydam for Ida Harris, Jane Schenk, and Jacob Harris.
- Series 3: Other Brooklyn land documents
  - Deed, 1698 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Johannes Fine bought 74 acres of land from Dorothy Verseiur [?] and Jocham, her son, of "Newtonne" [Newtown]. The property bordered that of Samuel Coe on the south side.
  - Deed, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Johannes Fine purchased land from Thomas Pettit.
  - Deed, 1710 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Johannes Fyn [Fine?], a blacksmith, bought land from Thomas Pettit of Newtown, Queens.
  - Mortgage, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Barrent Lefferts and his wife "Phebe" sold land to Lambert Suydam, Hendrik E. Suydam, Abraham Debevoise, Benjamin Linchman, Jeremiah Remsen, Martin Schenk, and Francis Skillman. Witnessed by Johannes E. Lott.
  - Mortgage, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Andrew Mercein mortgaged property to Isaac Harris located at Pearl and High Streets, Brooklyn. Formerly the property of Joshua Sands.
  - Deed, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Dr. Stephen C. Roe of New York City sold land in Onondonga County, NY to George Bushe of New York City.